<?xml version="1.0"?>
<s:slideset xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
            xmlns:s="http://www.oscom.org/2003/SlideML/1.0/"
            xml:lang="en-AU">
  <s:metadata>
    <s:title>PyORBit</s:title>
    <s:subtitle>an ORBit2 binding for Python</s:subtitle>

    <s:authorgroup>
      <s:author>
	<s:givenname>James</s:givenname>
	<s:familyname>Henstridge</s:familyname>
	<s:email>james@daa.com.au</s:email>
      </s:author>
    </s:authorgroup>

    <s:confgroup>
      <s:conftitle>GUADEC 2003</s:conftitle>
      <s:address>Dublin, Ireland</s:address>
    </s:confgroup>

    <s:abstract>
      <p>PyORBit is a new Python binding for the ORBit2 CORBA ORB.  It
      was developed in response to the needs of the gnome-python
      package.  It makes heavy use of the ORBit::IModule interfaces in
      ORBit2.  This allows us to efficiently build stubs at runtime
      from type-libs, rather than having to generate stub source files
      ahead of time.</p>
    </s:abstract>
  </s:metadata>

  <s:slide lang="en-AU">
    <s:title>Introduction</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>PyORBit is a Python binding for ORBit2</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Was written for use by the Python bindings for Gnome.</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>Should be useful on its own too though.</li>
	</ul>
	<li>Aims to follow the standard Python Language Mapping for
	CORBA.</li>
	<li>Uses ORBit2 type information to generate client stubs and
	server skeletons.</li>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
    <s:notes>
      <ul>
	<li>Python Language Mapping: <a
	href="http://www.omg.org/cgi-bin/doc?formal/02-09-07">http://www.omg.org/cgi-bin/doc?formal/02-09-07</a></li>
      </ul>
    </s:notes>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>History</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>ORBit 0.5.x bindings:</p>
      <ul>
	<li>orbit-python</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>Written by Jason Tackaberry</li>
	  <li>Took ideas from Owen Taylor's Perl bindings</li>
	  <li>Generated stubs and skeletons at runtime by parsing
	  IDL</li>
	  <li>Was the basis for Johan Dahlin's 1.x Bonobo bindings</li>
	</ul>
      </ul>
      <p>ORBit2 bindings:</p>
      <ul>
	<li>orbit2-python</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>A minimal port of orbit-python by Johan.</li>
	  <li>Used by earlier releases of the Gnome 2 Python
	  bindings.</li>
	  <li>Did not take advantage of many of ORBit2's newer
	  features.</li>
	  <li>Manually marshaled data to and from GIOP buffers.</li>
	</ul>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>PyORBit</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>Due to a number of shortcomings in orbit2-python, I started
      looking at doing a new binding that better suited the needs of
      the Gnome Python bindings.  Some features include:</p>
      <ul>
	<li>Make use of ORBit2 type-code information.</li>
	<li>Can generate stubs from ORBit2 type-libs, parsing IDL or by
	introspection.</li>
	<li>Can marshal from Python representation to and from C
	representation.</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>C code can invoke methods on in-process Python
	  objects.</li>
	  <li>Python code can invoke methods on in-process C
	  objects.</li>
	</ul>
	<li>Makes use of new features in Python 2.2.</li>
	<li>About 33% smaller than orbit-python.</li>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>Type Codes</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>In the CORBA framework, type codes are used to represent the
      various types of data that that can be transmitted.  They hold
      all the information the ORB needs to marshal and transmit data
      over the wire plus some metadata.</p>
      <p>This includes most of the information that a language binding
      needs to marshal data:</p>
      <ul>
	<li>fundamental type of data</li>
	<li>for enumerations, the list of value names.</li>
	<li>for structures and unions, the list of field names and types.</li>
	<li>for sequences and arrays, the type of the items.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Unfortunately, type codes do not provide much information
      about interfaces.</p>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>ORBit2 Interface Information</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>ORBit2 introduces a new way to represent information about
      interfaces through the use of the <tt>IInterface</tt> type:</p>

      <pre class="programlisting">struct IInterface {
  TypeCode tc;
  sequence&lt;IMethod&gt; methods;
  sequence&lt;string&gt; base_interfaces;
};</pre>

      <p>The fields are:</p>
      <ul>
	<li>The type code for this interface.</li>
	<li>a sequence of structures describing the interface's
	methods.</li>
	<li>a sequence of base interface names.</li>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>ORBit2 Interface Information</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>IMethod structures contain the following:</p>
      <ul>
	<li>name of method</li>
	<li>names and types of arguments, along with flags (in, out,
	inout).</li>
	<li>The type code for the return type.</li>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>How to Get Interface Information</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>ORBit2 provides a number of ways to obtain interface
      information:</p>
      <ul>
	<li><b>Type libraries:</b> these are shared libraries containing the
	IInterface structures for a set of interfaces as static data.
	Can be loaded with the <tt>ORBit_small_get_iinterface()</tt>
	function.</li>
	<li><b>IDL files:</b> ORBit2 provides an API to read in an IDL
	file and return interface information in the
	<tt>IInterface</tt> format.</li>
	<li><b>Introspection:</b> servers implemented using ORBit2
	automatically provide an <tt>ORBit_get_iinterface</tt>
	method.  This can be invoked to retrieve interface information
	about a particular server.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>PyORBit can use any of these methods to get interface
      information.</p>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>Method Invocation</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <ul>
	<li>Method invocation goes through the
	<tt>ORBit_small_invoke_stub()</tt> function.</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>Takes an <tt>IMethod</tt> structure that describes how
	  to perform the method invocation.</li>
	  <li>Is responsible for marshaling the argument vector from
	  C layout to a GIOP buffer for remote invocations.</li>
	  <li>For local invocations, no marshaling required.</li>
	</ul>
	<li>For language bindings, it is only necessary to implement
	functions to marshal to and from the language's native format
	and C format.</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>For local calls to C servers, ORBit2 can pass the values
	  directly to the server.</li>
	  <li>For remote calls, there are two translations, but this
	  gets lost in the noise.</li>
	</ul>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>Comparison with Interface Repository</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>CORBA standard defines an interface repository
      service.</p>
      <ul>
	<li>Never supported well by ORBit</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Some benefits of ORBit's approach include:</p>
      <ul>
	<li>No need for a separate server to hold interface info.</li>
	<li>No need to prime the interface repository with IDL before
	use.</li>
	<li>Interface information can be retrieved directly from
	servers.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>If interface repository support is desired, it should be
      possible to implement as a bridge that generates
      <tt>IInterface</tt> structures from the information in the
      repository.</p>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>PyORBit Stubs and Skeletons</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <ul>
	<li>Like its predecessor, PyORBit generates stubs and skeletons
        at runtime.</li>
	<li>However, PyORBit doesn't hook <tt>__import__</tt>.</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>You must manually load type-libs or IDL.</li>
	  <li>Some modules may automatically load up type-libs, such as
	  <tt>bonobo</tt>.</li>
	</ul>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>PyORBit Stubs</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <ul>
	<li>Stubs are new style Python classes.</li>
	<li>CORBA methods are represented by a "CORBA method"
	type.</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>wraps a <tt>IMethod</tt>.</li>
	  <li>Acts as a descriptor, as with standard methods.</li>
	</ul>
	<li>Provides automatically generated doc strings, so that
	<tt>help()</tt> works.</li>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>PyORBit Skeletons</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <ul>
	<li>Follows the standard Python mapping.</li>
	<li>Like the client side stubs, skeletons are generated at
	runtime.</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>As with stubs, <tt>IInterface</tt> data is used to generate
	  the skeleton</li>
	</ul>
	<li>ORBit2 allows a servant to provide an "implementation
	finder" function responsible for finding the implementation of
	a method.</li>
	<li>ORBit2 passes arguments to the servant in the same format
	given to <tt>ORBit_small_invoke_stub()</tt>, so we can reuse
	the same marshaling code.</li>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>Simple Scripting Example</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>In this example, we will use PyORBit to tell the running
      Nautilus process to open a window at a particular location.</p>

      <p>First we need to get the IOR of the Nautilus shell.  We could
      use the Gnome Python bindings for this, but to reduce the amount
      of magic, I'll use the standard <tt>activation-client</tt>
      program.</p>

      <pre class="programlisting"><b>$</b> activation-client -s "iid == 'OAFIID:Nautilus_Shell'"
Query spec is "iid == 'OAFIID:Nautilus_Shell'"
Activation ID "OAFAID:[OAFIID:Nautilus_Factory,james,example.net]" RESULT_OBJECT
IOR:01daffbf17000000...
<b>$</b></pre>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>Simple Scripting Example</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>First we start Python:</p>

      <pre class="programlisting">
<b>&gt;&gt;&gt;</b> import ORBit
<b>&gt;&gt;&gt;</b> import CORBA
<b>&gt;&gt;&gt;</b> orb = CORBA.ORB_init()</pre>

      <p>Now we create an object reference from the IOR (which will
      also generate a stub for the Nautilus::Shell interface):</p>

      <pre class="programlisting"><b>&gt;&gt;&gt;</b> shell = orb.string_to_object('IOR:01daffbf17000000...')</pre>

      <p>Now we can call methods on the object reference:</p>

      <pre class="programlisting"><b>&gt;&gt;&gt;</b> shell.open_windows(['fonts:///'], '')</pre>

    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>More Advanced Scripting Example</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <p>Nautilus metadata monitoring: <a
      href="metadata-demo.py">metadata-demo.py</a>.</p>
      <ul>
	<li>Uses the <tt>Nautilus::MetafileFactory</tt>
	interface.</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>This is a private interface, subject to change</li>
	</ul>
	<li>Loading interface data from typelibs or from IDL
	files.</li>
	<li>Implements the Nautilus::MetafileMonitor interface.</li>
	<li>Asks for metadata change notification for files in the
	home directory.</li>
	<li>Prints the list of emblems for files that change.</li>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

  <s:slide>
    <s:title>Future</s:title>
    <s:content>
      <ul>
	<li>Further development of the CORBA related Gnome bindings.</li>
	<li>Custom interfaces on Bonobo components.</li>
	<li>Integrate better with threaded applications.</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>Looking at the new Python 2.3 threading APIs.</li>
	</ul>
      </ul>
    </s:content>
  </s:slide>

</s:slideset>

<!--  LocalWords:  Bonobo
 -->
